so hi i am
i wanted to ask you your questions how
did you start your yoga journey and how
has it been for
the last so many years so as a little
child
i had i actually had a asthma and
bronchitis and i always had a lot of
respiratory
you know issues so my mom is a yoga
teacher a yoga practitioner and she
always made me do pranayam but she made
it
become very fun she never told me i was
doing yoga so she would make me do all
these different kind of breathing
exercises etc
so growing up i always practiced it but
i didn't know that i was practicing
uh you know pranayama or littlest part
of the
yogic lifestyle uh very recently
uh i'm an actual i'm a commercial pilot
and i was about to
start flying with the airlines and i got
into a very very bad near fatal bike
accident
which led me to be medically unfit for a
very long time
after that is when i started yoga
therapy after physiotherapy and i
enjoyed it so much and i got
went and i got a yoga teacher's training
because when you go through
some trauma where you're bedridden for
almost a year
the physical uh physical trauma really
heals but it's the mental trauma i think
that you know you just can't put a
band-aid on or just have medication and
just
get better so that was something i was
working on every day and that's when
i uh i was introduced to this beautiful
world i
i got a teacher's training i got so
interested in the philosophy the asanas
and how it was benefiting me
and that's it and then i realized that
this is something that i need to do
every single day like
every single morning when i wake up for
me yoga is just not about asana or not
about breath work
or not about meditation there's eight
limbs of yoga there's so much more it's
like like i know that you also practice
this as a lifestyle so
you uh i mean i know you know better
than anyone else what i mean so every
single day it's
working on yourself so i feel like the
whole eight limbs of yoga is something
that
i really treat as a philosophy for my
own lifestyle to understand to be
healthier
to be more holistic to be more present
and that's what's really
gotten me through so this is where i am
today after many years
yeah well said i have seen that most of
the people who are very passionate about
yoga they have some background of some
um
life threatening something uh so about i
and this this undying passion doesn't
come
without those kind of things that i have
seen in most of the cases
now i have one question from one of our
employees since most of us are working
from home nowadays
and this is causing us a lot of mental
stress
so can you tell us some techniques while
working
or while taking short breaks between
calls
which we can practice so that it will
help us uh
going through it absolutely so a few
things that i
understand is movement is very very
important so just don't plateau don't
stagnate yourself so even after when
you're working from home and especially
with your posture
bad posture can cause discomfort bad
posture can also
stress and posture are the same thing
you will feel a lot of stress and stress
is just not physical stress it will
translate into mental stress as well
so a few things that i'm going to show
you movement base if you're somebody who
sits on a chair
i'm going to do this sideways and you're
always on a desk
just push your chair back fold your leg
like this and go forward
when you do this you're going to feel
the the side of the leg that's
on top your buttock stretch you can do
this on both sides
this is really really good to help you
to open the hips up
the twist that i was showing you use a
chair and twist
if you need to do a downward dog hold on
to the chair and push into a downward
dog this is also great for the shoulders
if you want
something which is slightly higher you
can do it on a slightly higher chair
so when it comes to movement and just
walk around that's extremely important
another thing to do is just breathing
so breath work and when you hold your
breath
tension it actually helps you to
activate your parasympathetic nervous
system so think about
that is causing you to stay karma which
in turn
brings the stress down so something that
i really enjoy doing is called box
breathing
so i want you to visualize a square what
you can do is close your eyes
start at the bottom point of the square
inhale when you go up the square
hold your breath in till you go to the
opposite side of the square
exhale when you come down the square and
again
don't inhale don't exhale suspend your
breath till you come back
so what i do i start with square equal
sides of three seconds so inhale three
hold three exhale three suspend your
breath for three seconds you can do that
for three rounds
then you can do three rounds or four
seconds then you can do three rounds or
five seconds so automatically your
kumbaka which is your retention of your
breath
keeps improving per cycle so that if
you're just mindful even for a minute
automatically you will feel a little
more better rested
your stress levels really work with your
hormones so once your hormones are also
balanced
all of this activates that
parasympathetic nervous system which
helps you to calm down
so these are the two things that i
definitely recommend and of course
always hydrate eat well
but more than that movement stretching
in between long sessions of sitting at
home
and breathing correctly it is said that
people
don't live ears they live the number of
breaths for example the dog
he breathes very fast and he lives for
12 years
and human beings who breathe relatively
slowly they live longer
so we are well excited about this now
another question that somebody has sent
us
is that you teach a lot of celebrities
so is there any difference when you
teach them and
or something particular that you keep in
mind while teaching them
yes and no every i mean every every
every every student as a teacher i feel
that
any kind of teacher you you cannot you
forget if you're teaching a celebrity if
you're teaching
xyz it's the same thing however i do
realize that celebrities though
especially a lot of uh the celebrities
in the movies have an extremely erratic
lifestyle
because they have they have crazy hours
they have to wake up at
crazy times and they always have
sometimes they have a specific goal that
they need to achieve
so i will alter a few things for them
which means maybe i will do a high
intensity
yoga asana practice but i will still
stick to the traditional routes of
not forgetting what the practice is
about so maybe that i will tweak a
little
but apart from that i truly believe that
everybody's practice
is different because everybody every
individual is different so sometimes
when a student
comes into a class they don't want a
high pace you know that energy they need
something more calmer similarly if i'm
practicing in the morning i will do a
more uh
refreshing or a more recharging uh
practice which is called your surya
namaskar for example in the evening
we'll do a chandra namaskar we will not
do a surya namaskar because you don't
want to
at 8 30 or maybe at eight o'clock in the
evening you can't do that because then
you won't be able to sleep well
so depending on those alterations of
course there is no there is as a teacher
there is really no difference apart from
what goals they want to achieve
yeah a lot of celebrities want to lose
their weight very very quickly
for for example their next movie is
starting and they want to lose 10 kgs in
maybe 2 weeks
i don't think it is healthy but but
still they have to go that is their
professional hazard
they have to go through it and they're
so getting into my next question there
are many international celebrities
who have got attracted towards yoga
madonna is one of them
i know uh there is a very famous
violinist
maybe you know i know his name uh his
name was
so he was a violinist who uh who got
taught by bks anger my guru
so he got attracted to yoga long back in
60s
uh so what what is it that these
international celebrities who have no
hindu or indian culture
background uh get them attracted to this
kind of yoga
i think the holistic approach of the
lifestyle i think
baby holistic wellness and well-being is
so important and i
somehow i truly believe and i have seen
the shift that
even though yoga has originated the
practice of yoga has originated
from us from india i feel that a lot of
people especially the millennials
especially gen z
and they all get attracted to what's
going on in the west
so in one way i'm extremely happy
because when people see
that then that's what they want to
incorporate into their life a little
more
but big like i have studied a lot of
teachers trainings in the west and what
i realized is that
they go seeking for a holistic practice
because there is
i mean uh earlier the people who didn't
do yoga were just going to the gym
burning calories looking amazing but
internally they were not at peace
and then when they found this practice
they realized that it's just not
about a makeover on the outside you can
look beautiful on the upside but it's
what's inside that counts
and i realized that that's what they
found with yoga that's why i feel that
the shift has happened the holistic
approach towards the lifestyle and
and your own well-being yeah
actually yoga is more to do with mental
than physical
but initially most people who get
attracted to yoga it is because of the
physical benefits
and then they slowly move on to the
mental benefits absolutely
so a lot of people have been facing
mental issues during this fandamage
and they are worried about when the next
pandemic will hate or why
so basically how do you build the mental
strength
uh by doing your yoga uh you know so i
talk i
i feel of course mental strength is not
something that is consistent every
single day
you know you have to make that choice to
be strong and
even with me even though i've been
practicing for a long time even i have
my days where
sometimes especially through this
pandemic because it's so new to all of
us
we don't know what's going on we don't
know what's next but what i realized is
there are few things that you can
which are in your control and i think a
yoga practice
makes you understand that because it it
helps your hormones your hormones place
so much
of an importance to what your thought
your thoughts as well
so when your hormones are balanced when
you're working your meditation
is activating a parasympathetic nervous
system it's allowing you to think with a
little more clarity
for example i am i can be responsible to
improve my immunity i can eat well
i can sleep well again sleep a lot of
people who eat well and then they just
work out a lot but they don't sleep well
then they wonder why they are stressed
and they wonder why their body is not
changing a certain way
so what this practice has taught me is
that do whatever is in your control
and then you have to learn to detach so
like i said there's a little more
philosophy i know
you you will understand but for
beginners to understand that
that it's also about detachment to learn
that so what is in your control is what
you focus on so
especially through these times focus on
your breath
focus on building immunity focus on
building a routine sleep well
and then that's that's all is in your
control and then you just have to let go
so these are the things that i really
helped that in turn build up more mental
strength
now this uh brings me to the last of the
questions that have been uh
asked uh is is yoga
a way of life or is it a physical
exercise or some
mental well-being meditation kind of a
technique
yoga is a holistic
lifestyle for me it is
and yes those side effects are
mental well-being even losing weight is
a side effect and all the goodness comes
along with it
so yoga is something i think when we
when we translate yoga we think yoga is
about doing asanas or doing a head stand
or doing something or doing a split or
losing weight but yoga is
the eight limbs of yoga which is
comprises of
a lot of elements
a lot of elements of being
mindful in tune
and focusing it's mind body soul
yeah well said
thanks a lot anshuka
if she's there yeah yes sir thank you
very much
thank you very much anshuka for
answering all those questions thank you
very much mr agarwal
for taking us to these questions and of
course the discussion was very
enlightening